Guide to the New Haven West Association Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
New Haven West Association records
1787-1909
GEN MSS 1296
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes) + 1 art
The collection contains bound volumes of manuscript meeting minutes for the New Haven West Association, along with other records and papers related to the business of the association such as missions to New York State and cases regarding specific clergy members. Also present are meeting minutes for the New Haven West Conference of Churches, the constitution of the Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County, a printed memorial to Reverend William Patton, and a decorated trunk that formerly held the records.
New Haven West Association (Conn.)
Patton, William W. (William Weston), 1821-1889
Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County (Conn.)
New Haven West Conference of Churches (Conn.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New Haven West Association, 1916-1936.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
New Haven East Association Records (GEN MSS 1295), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
New Haven West Association
The Association of the County of New-Haven, an organization of Connecticut Congregational ministers, was formed in 1709 following a meeting of twelve ministers and four church laymen called by the colonial legislature. Held in Saybrook, Connecticut, the meeting resulted in the "Saybrook Platform," a new constitution for the Congregational Church in Connecticut, which gave associations the responsibility to examine candidates for the ministry, and to oversee the behavior of the ministers. In 1787 the association was divided to form the New Haven East Association and the New Haven West Association, with the course of the Quinnipiac River as the geographical line. The two organizations were again united by unanimous resolution in 1893 to form the New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers in Connecticut. That organization merged with the New Haven Central Association in 1903.
The Consociation of the County of New-Haven, an organization of Congregational churches and pastors also formed in 1709, was devoted to the management of ecclesiastical discipline. That organization, with a membership composed of both church members and pastors, could impose discipline on specific churches and judge disputes that arose. It later evolved into two separate bodies called the New Haven East Consociation (established in 1787) and the Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County (established in 1799).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains bound volumes of manuscript meeting minutes for the New Haven West Association, along with other records and papers related to the business of the association such as missions to New York State and cases regarding specific clergy members. Also present are meeting minutes for the New Haven West Conference of Churches, the constitution of the Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County, a printed memorial to Rev. William Patton, and a decorated trunk that formerly held the records.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Meeting Minutes, 1787-1909. II. Other Records and Papers, 1787-1879.
Clergy -- Connecticut; Congregationalism -- Clergy; New Haven County (Conn.) -- Religious life and customs; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 18th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 19th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 20th Century; Trunks (containers) -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 19th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 18th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 19th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 20th Century; Bacon, Leonard, 1802-1881; Kendall, John B. (John Ballard), 1799-1888; MacWhorter, Alexander, 1822-1880; Magill, Seagrove W. (Seagrove William), 1810-1884; Patton, William, 1798-1879; Patton, William W. (William Weston), 1821-1889 ( Filial tribute to the memory of Rev. William Patton, D.D.); Read, Nathan S., -1821; Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County (Conn.); New Haven West Association (Conn.); New Haven West Conference of Churches (Conn.)
- Meeting Minutes, 1787-1909; Series I; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: New Haven West Association and New Haven West Conference of Churches.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains four bound volumes and one folder of manuscript meeting minutes.
  - New Haven West Association
    - Volume I, 1787-1814 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Volume II, 1814-1832 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Volume III, 1832-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Other minutes, 1815-1848 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Haven West Conference of Churches
    - Volume I, 1865-1909 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Other Records and Papers, 1787-1879; Series II; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  Series II contains other records and papers related to the business of the association, including those on missions to New York State, and letters, reports, and testimonials relating to cases regarding specific clergy members. Also present is the constitution of the Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County, a printed memorial to Rev. William Patton, and a decorated trunk that formerly held the records.
  - Ecclesiastical Constitution of the Consociation of the Western District of the County of New Haven, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Certificates of church membership, applications for letters of admission and recommendations to associations and ordinations, 1814-1892 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Creeds, 1839-1847 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Reports on various matters, complaints, etc., 1806-1877 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Papers relating to missions to New York State, 1787-1809 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters, reports, and testimonials relating to the case of Nathan S. Read, 1813-1815 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters and statements regarding Seagrove W. Magill, 1834-1835 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters, reports, and testimonials relating to the case of John B. Kendall, 1836-1837 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Papers relating to the case of Alexander MacWhorter, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Obituary notices (copied from original sources), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous documents relating to the association and individuals, 1796-1879 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous documents relating to the association and individuals, 1788-1874 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Filial Tribute to the Memory of Rev. William Patton, D.D., by William W. Patton, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Trunk formerly holding records, undated (Box 4 (Art))